<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="bcp" docName="draft-dickinson-bcp-op-00">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private=""?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="DNS Privacy Service Recommendations">Recommendations for DNS Privacy Service Operators</title>

<author initials="S." surname="Dickinson" fullname="Sara Dickinson">
<organization>Sinodun IT</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<street>Magdalen Centre</street>
<street>Oxford Science Park</street>
<city>Oxford</city>
<code>OX4 4GA</code>
<country>United Kingdom</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>sara@sinodun.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="B." surname="Overeinder" fullname="Benno J. Overeinder">
<organization>NLnet Labs</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<street>Science Park 140</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<code>1098 XH</code>
<country>The Netherlands</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>benno@nlnetLabs.nl</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="R." surname="van Rijswijk-Deij" fullname="Roland M. van Rijswijk-Deij">
<organization>SURFnet bv</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<street>PO Box 19035 </street>
<city>Utrecht</city>
<code>3501 DA Utrecht</code>
<country>The Netherlands</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>roland.vanrijswijk@surfnet.nl</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Mankin" fullname="Allison Mankin">
<organization>Salesforce</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<code></code>
<country></country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>allison.mankin@gmail.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2018" month="March" day="5"/>

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>dprive</workgroup>
<keyword>DNS</keyword>


<abstract>
<t>This document presents operational, policy and security considerations for DNS
operators who choose to offer DNS Privacy services.
</t>
<t>This document also presents a framework to assist writers of DNS Privacy Policy
and Practices Statements (analogous to DNS Security Extensions (DNSSEC) Policies
and DNSSEC Practice Statements described in <xref target="RFC6841"/>).
</t>
</abstract>


</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>[NOTE: This document is submitted to the IETF for initial review and for
feedback on the best forum for future versions of this document. Discussion of
DoH <xref target="I-D.ietf-doh-dns-over-https"/> is included here
in anticipation of that draft progressing to be an RFC.]
</t>
<t>The Domain Name System (DNS) is at the core of the Internet; almost every
activity on the Internet starts with a DNS query (and often several). However
the DNS was not originally designed with strong security or privacy mechanisms.
A number of developments have taken place in recent years which aim to increase
the privacy of the DNS system and these are now seeing some deployment. This
latest evolution of the DNS presents new challenges to operators and this
document attempts to provide an overview of considerations for privacy focussed
DNS services.
</t>
<t>In recent years there has also been an increase in the availability of &quot;open
resolvers&quot; <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-bis"/> which users may prefer to use
instead of the default network resolver because they offer a specific feature
(e.g. good reachability, encrypted transport, strong privacy policy, filtering
(or lack of), etc.). These open resolvers have tended to be at the forefront of
adoption of privacy related enhancements but it is anticipated that operators of
other resolver services will follow.
</t>
<t>Whilst protocols that encrypt DNS messages on the wire provide protection
against certain attacks, the resolver operator still has (in principle) full
visibility of the query data for each user. Therefore, a trust relationship
exists. The ability of the operator to provide a transparent, well documented,
and secure privacy service will likely serve as a major differentiating factor
for privacy conscious users.
</t>
<t>It should also be noted that the choice of a user to configure a single resolver
(or a fixed set of resolvers) and an encrypted transport to use in all network
environments has both advantages and disadvantages. For example the user has a
clear expectation of which resolvers have visibility of their query data however
this resolver/transport selection may provide an added mechanism to track them
as they move across network environments.
</t>
<t>More recently the global legislative landscape with regard to personal data
collection, retention, and psuedonymization has seen significant activity with
differing requirements active in different jurisdictions. For example the user
of a service and the service itself may be in jurisdictions with conflicting
legislation. It is an untested area that simply using a DNS resolution service
constitutes consent from the user for the operator to process their query data.
The impact of recent legislative changes on data pertaining to the users of both
Internet Service Providers and DNS open resolvers is not fully understood at the
time of writing.
</t>
<t>This document has two main goals:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>To provide operational guidance related to DNS over encrypted
transports and to outline recommendations for data handling for
operators of DNS privacy services.</t>
<t>To introduce the DNS Privacy Policy
and Practice Statement (DPPPS) and present a framework to assist writers of
this document. A DPPPS is a document an operator can publish
outlining their operational practices and commitments with regard to privacy
providing a means for clients to evaluate the privacy properties of a given DNS
privacy service. In particular, the framework identifies the elements that
should be considered in formulating a DPPPS. It does not, however, define a
particular Policy or Practice Statement, nor does it seek to provide legal
advice or recommendations as to the contents.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Community knowledge about operational practices can change quickly, and
experience shows that a Best Current Practice (BCP) document about privacy and
security is a point-in-time statement. Readers are advised to seek out any
errata or updates that apply to this document.
</t>

<section anchor="scope" title="Scope">
<t>Whilst <xref target="RFC7626"/> describes the privacy issues and risks associated
with the use of the DNS by Internet users. This document is concerned with
best practice considerations for operators providing DNS privacy services. It
includes (but is not limited to) considerations in the following areas (taken from <xref target="RFC7626"/>):
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>Data on the wire between a stub and a resolver</t>
<t>Data &quot;at rest&quot; on a recursive server (e.g. in logs)</t>
<t>Data sent onwards from the resolver either on the wire or shared with a third
party</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Whilst the issues raised here are targeted at those operators who choose to
offer a DNS Privacy service, considerations for areas 2 and 3 could equally
apply to operators who offer DNS only over unencrypted transports but who would
like to align with privacy best practice.
</t>
<t>Privacy considerations specifically from the perspective of an end user, or
those for operators of authoritative nameservers are out of scope.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="documents" title="Documents">
<t>There are various documents that describe protocol changes that have the
potential to either increase or decrease the privacy of the DNS. Note this does
not imply that some documents are good or bad, better or worse, just that (for
example) some features may bring functional benefits at the price of a reduction
in privacy and conversely some features increase privacy with an accompanying
increase in complexity. A selection of the most relevant documents are listed in
the following three sections for reference, however, this is neither an
exhaustive list nor a definitive statement on the characteristic of the
document.
</t>

<section anchor="documents-with-the-potential-to-increase-dns-privacy" title="Documents with the potential to increase DNS privacy">
<t>These documents are limited in scope to communications between stub
clients and recursive resolvers:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>'Specification for DNS over Transport Layer Security (TLS)' <xref target="RFC7858"/>,
referred to here as simply 'DNS-over-TLS'.</t>
<t>'DNS over Datagram Transport Layer Security (DTLS)' <xref target="RFC8094"/>, referred to
here simply as 'DNS-over-DTLS'. Note that this document has the Category of
Experimental.</t>
<t>'DNS Queries over HTTPS (DoH)' <xref target="I-D.ietf-doh-dns-over-https"/></t>
<t>'Usage Profiles for DNS over TLS and DNS over DTLS' <xref target="RFC8310"/></t>
<t>'The EDNS(0) Padding Option' <xref target="RFC7830"/> and 'Padding Policy for EDNS(0)' <xref target="I-D.ietf-dprive-padding-policy"/></t>
</list>
</t>
<t>These documents apply to recursive to authoritative DNS but are relevant when
considering the operation of a recursive server:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>'DNS Query Name Minimisation to Improve Privacy' <xref target="RFC7816"/> referred to here as simply 'QNAME minimization'</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="documents-with-the-potential-to-decrease-dns-privacy" title="Documents with the potential to decrease DNS privacy">
<t>These documents relate to functionality that could provide increased tracking of
user activity as a side effect:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Client Subnet in DNS Queries <xref target="RFC7871"/></t>
<t>DNS Cookies <xref target="RFC7873"/>)</t>
<t>TLS session resumption <xref target="RFC5077"/></t>
<t>A DNS Packet Capture Format <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-capture-format"/></t>
<t>Passive DNS TODO: need ref</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="related-operational-documents" title="Related operational documents">
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>DNS Transport over TCP - Implementation Requirements <xref target="RFC7766"/></t>
<t>Operational requirements for DNS-over-TCP <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-tcp-requirements"/></t>
<t>The edns-tcp-keepalive EDNS0 Option <xref target="RFC7828"/></t>
<t>DNS Stateful Operations <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-session-signal"/></t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
<t>The key words described in <xref target="RFC8174"/> are not used in this document because the
intention here is not to prescribe policy but to provide indicators of best
practice. Therefore, in order to give some guidance on the importance of the
various recommendations in this document the following terms are
used in descending order of importance
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>EXPECTED (similar to <xref target="RFC8174"/> MUST)</t>
<t>OUGHT (similar to <xref target="RFC8174"/> OUGHT)</t>
<t>MIGHT (similar to <xref target="RFC8174"/> MAY)</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Privacy terminology is as described in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC6973"/>.
</t>
<t>DNS terminology is as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-bis"/>
with the following additions:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Privacy-enabling DNS server: A DNS server (most likely a Full-service
resolver) that implements DNS-over-TLS [RFC7858] and/or DOH
<xref target="I-D.ietf-doh-dns-over-https"/>, and may optionally implement DNS-over-DTLS
[RFC8094]. A DNS-over-(D)TLS server should also offer at least one of the
credentials described in Section 8 of <xref target="RFC8310"/> and implement the (D)TLS
profile described in Section 9 of <xref target="RFC8310"/>.

<vspace/></t>
</list>
</t>
<t>[TODO: This updates <xref target="RFC8310"/>]
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>DPPPS: DNS Privacy Policy and Practice Statement, see
<xref target="dns-privacy-policy-and-practice-statement"/>.</t>
<t>DNS privacy service: The service that is offered via a privacy-enabling DNS
server and is documented either in an informal statement of policy and
practice with regard to users privacy or a formal DPPPS.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="recommendations-for-dns-privacy-services" title="Recommendations for DNS Privacy Services">

<section anchor="transport-recommendations" title="Transport recommendations">
<t>A DNS privacy service is EXPECTED to be made available over one or more of the following transports
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>DNS-over-TLS</t>
<t>DNS-over-HTTPS</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>A DNS privacy service OUGHT also be provided over DNS-over-DTLS, IPSec, DNSCrypt
or VPNs. However, use of these transports for DNS are not standardized and any
discussion of best practice for providing such service is out of scope for this
document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="protocol-recommendations" title="Protocol recommendations">
<t>In the case of DNS-over-TLS, TLS profiles from Section 9 and the Countermeasures
to DNS Traffic Analysis from section 11.1 of <xref target="RFC8310"/> are EXPECTED to be used. This includes but is not limited to:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Implementing only (D)TLS 1.2 or later</t>
<t>Adhering to <xref target="RFC7525"/></t>
<t>Implementing EDNS(0) Padding [RFC7830]</t>
<t>Honoring a SOURCE PREFIX-LENGTH set to 0 in a query containing the EDNS(0)
Client subnet option</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>DNS privacy services OUGHT also consider the following capabilities/options:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>QNAME minimisation <xref target="RFC7816"/></t>
<t>No use of the EDNS(0) Client subnet option in upstream queries</t>
<t>Implementing <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-dnssec-chain-extension"/></t>
<t>Providing TLSA DANE records for the nameserver</t>
<t>Management of TLS connections to optimise performance for clients using either
<list style="symbols">
<t><xref target="RFC7766"/> and EDNS(0) Keepalive <xref target="RFC7828"/> and/or</t>
<t>DNS Stateful Operations <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-session-signal"/></t>
</list></t>
<t>Clients should not be required to use TLS session resumption <xref target="RFC5077"/> or Domain Name System (DNS) Cookies <xref target="RFC7873"/></t>
</list>
</t>
<t>DNS privacy services MIGHT offer the following capabilities:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>A DNS privacy service on both port 853 and 443 (to circumvent blocking of
port 853)</t>
<t>A .onion <xref target="RFC7686"/> service endpoint</t>
<t>Aggressive Use of DNSSEC-Validated Cache <xref target="RFC8198"/> to reduce the number of
queries to authoritative servers to increase privacy.</t>
<t>Run a copy of the root zone on loopback <xref target="RFC7706"/> to avoid making queries to
the root servers that might leak information.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="service-recommendations" title="Service recommendations">

<section anchor="availability" title="Availability">
<t>DNS privacy services are EXPECTED be engineered for high availability. A failed
DNS privacy service could force the user to switch providers, fallback to
cleartext or accept no DNS service for the outage.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="service-options" title="Service options">
<t>A DNS privacy service should not differ from the service offered on un-encrypted
channels in terms of such options as filtering (or lack of), DNSSEC validation,
etc. To do so would unfairly disadvantage users of the privacy service.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="client-query-obfuscation" title="Client query obfuscation">
<t>Since queries from recursive resolvers to authoritative servers are performed
using cleartext (at the time of writing), resolver services need to consider the
extent to which they may be directly leaking information about their client
community via these upstream queries and what they can do to mitigate this
further. Note, that even when all the relevant techniques described above are
employed there may still be attacks possible, e.g.
<xref target="Pitfalls-of-DNS-Encryption"/>. For example, a resolver with a very small
community of users risks exposing data in this way and OUGHT obfuscate this
traffic by mixing it with 'generated' traffic to make client characterisation
harder. The resolver OUGHT also employ aggressive pre-fetch techniques as a
further measure to counter traffic analysis.
</t>
<t>At the time of writing there are no standardized or widely recognized techniques
to preform such obfuscation or bulk pre-fetches.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="authentication-of-dns-privacy-services" title="Authentication of DNS privacy services">
<t>To enable users to select a 'Strict Privacy' usage profile
<xref target="RFC8310"/> DNS privacy services should provide
credentials in the form of either X.509 certificates, SPKI pinsets or TLSA
records. This in effect commits the DNS privacy service to a public identity
users will trust.
</t>
<t>Anecdotal evidence to date highlights this requirement as one of the more
challenging aspects for operators of traditional DNS resolvers that choose to
additionally provide a DNS privacy service as management of such credentials is
new to those DNS operators.
</t>

<section anchor="generation-and-publication-of-certificates" title="Generation and publication of certificates">
<t>It is recommended that operators:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Choose a short, memorable authentication name for their service</t>
<t>Automate the generation and publication of certificates</t>
<t>Monitor certificates to prevent accidental expiration of certificates</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="operational-management" title="Operational management">

<section anchor="limitations-of-using-a-pure-tls-proxy" title="Limitations of using a pure TLS proxy">
<t>Some operators may choose to implement DNS-over-TLS using a TLS proxy (e.g.
<eref target="https://nginx.org/">nginx</eref>, <eref target="https://www.haproxy.org/">haproxy</eref> or
<eref target="https://kb.isc.org/article/AA-01386/0/DNS-over-TLS.html">stunnel</eref>) in front of
a DNS nameserver because of proven robustness and capacity when handling large
numbers of client connections, load balancing capabilities and good tooling.
Currently, however, because such proxies typically have no specific handling of
DNS as a protocol over TLS or DTLS using them can restrict traffic management at
the proxy layer and at the DNS server. For example, all traffic received by a
nameserver behind such a proxy will appear to originate from the proxy and DNS
techniques such as ACLs or RRL will be hard or impossible to implement in the
nameserver.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="server-data-handling" title="Server data handling">
<t>The following are common activities for DNS service operators and in all cases
should be minimised or completely avoided if possible for DNS privacy services.
If data is retained it should be encrypted and either aggregated,
psuedonymised or anonymised whenever possible.
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Transient data (e.g. that used for real time monitoring and threat analysis
which might be held only memory) is OUGHT be retained for the shorted period
deemed operationally feasible.</t>
<t>Retention of DNS traffic logs OUGHT be only that required to sustain
operation of the service and, to the extent that such exists, meet regulatory
requirements.</t>
<t>DNS privacy services OUGHT not track users except for the particular purpose
of detecting and remedying technically malicious (e.g. DoS) or anomalous use
of the service</t>
<t>Operators OUGHT not provide data to third-parties without explicit consent
from users (we take the stance here that simply using the resolution service
itself does not constitute consent).</t>
<t>Data access OUGHT be minimised to only those
personal who require access to perform operational duties.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>TODO: Data for research vs operations... how to still motivate operators to share anonymised data?
</t>

<section anchor="psuedonymisation-and-anonymisation-methods" title="Psuedonymisation and anonymisation methods">
<t>There is active discussion in the space of effective psuedonymisation of
personal data in DNS query logs. To-date this has focussed on
psuedonymisation of client IP addresses, however there are as yet no
standards for this that are unencumbered by patents. This section briefly
references some known methods in this space at the time of writing.
</t>

<section anchor="ipcipher" title="ipcipher">
<t><xref target="ipcipher-spec"/> is a psuedonymisation technique which encrypts IPv4 and IPv6
addresses such that any address encrypts to a valid address. At the time of
writing the specification is under review and may be the subject of a future
IETF draft.
</t>
<t>NOTE: There are some significant security concerns about the use of ipcipher
that have been voiced by the ipcipher authors and its inclusion here should be
reviewed.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="bloom-filters" title="Bloom filters">
<t>There is also on-going work in the area of using Bloom filters as a
privacy-enhancing technology for DNS monitoring <xref target="DNS-bloom-filter"/>. The goal of
this work is to allow operators to identify so-called Indicators of Compromise
(IOCs) originating from specific subnets without storing information about, or
be able to monitor the DNS queries of an individual user.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="dns-privacy-policy-and-practice-statement" title="DNS privacy policy and practice statement">

<section anchor="recommended-contents-of-a-dppps" title="Recommended contents of a DPPPS">
<t>1 Policy.
</t>
<t>1.1 Recommendations. This section should explain, with reference to section
      <xref target="recommendations-for-dns-privacy-services"/> of this document which
      recommendations the DNS privacy service employs.
</t>
<t>1.2. Data handling. This section should explain, with reference to section
       <xref target="server-data-handling"/>
       of this document the policy for gathering and disseminating information
       collected by the DNS privacy service.
</t>
<t>1.2.1. Specify clearly what data (including whether it is aggregated,
        psuedonymised or anonymized) is:
</t>
<t>1.2.1.1. Collected and retained by the operator (and for how long)
</t>
<t>1.2.1.2. Shared with, sold or rented to third-parties
</t>
<t>1.2.2 Specify any exceptions to the above, for example technically malicious or
anomalous behaviour
</t>
<t>1.2.3 Declare any third-party affiliations or funding
</t>
<t>1.2.4 Whether user DNS data is correlated or combined with any other personal
    information held by the operator
</t>
<t>2 Practice. This section should explain the current operational practices of the service.
</t>
<t>2.1 Specify any temporary or permanent deviations from the policy for
    operational reasons
</t>
<t>2.2 Provide specific details of which capabilities are provided on which
      address and ports
</t>
<t>2.3 Specify the authentication name to be used (if any)
</t>
<t>2.4 Specify the SPKI pinsets to be used (if any) and policy for rolling keys
</t>
<t>2.5 Provide a contact email address for the service
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="current-privacy-statements" title="Current privacy statements">
<t>NOTE: An analysis of these statements will clearly only provide a snapshot at
the time of writing. It is included in this version of the draft to provide a
basis for the assessment of the contents of the DPPPS and is expected to be
removed or substantially re-worked in a future version.
</t>

<section anchor="google" title="Google">
<t><eref target="https://developers.google.com/speed/public-dns/privacy"/>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="quad9" title="Quad9">
<t><eref target="https://www.quad9.net/policy/"/>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="opendns" title="OpenDNS">
<t><eref target="https://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/about/legal/privacy-full.html"/>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="cloudflare" title="Cloudflare">
<t><eref target="https://developers.cloudflare.com/1.1.1.1/commitment-to-privacy/"/>
<eref target="https://developers.cloudflare.com/1.1.1.1/commitment-to-privacy/privacy-policy/privacy-policy/"/>
<eref target="https://developers.cloudflare.com/1.1.1.1/commitment-to-privacy/privacy-policy/firefox/"/>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="enforcementaccountability" title="Enforcement/accountability">
<t>Transparency reports may help with building user trust that operators adhere to their policies and practices.
</t>
<t>Independent monitoring should be performed where possible of:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>ECS, QNAME minimisation, EDNS(0) padding, etc.</t>
<t>Filtering</t>
<t>Uptime</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA considerations">
<t>None
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security considerations">
<t>TODO: e.g. New issues for DoS defence, server admin policies
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>Many thanks to Amelia Andersdotter for a very thorough review of this document
and to John Dickinson for review of and input to the early drafts of this
document.
</t>
<t>Thanks to John Todd for discussions on this topic.
</t>
<t>Sara Dickinson thanks the Open Technology Fund for a grant to support the work
on this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="changelog" title="Changelog">
<t>draft-dickinson-dprive-bcp-op-001
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>reworked the Terminology, Introduction and Scope</t>
<t>Added Document section</t>
<t>Applied most of Amelia Andersdotter's suggested changes.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>draft-dickinson-dprive-bcp-op-00
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Initial commit</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-session-signal.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-doh-dns-over-https.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dprive-padding-policy.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5077.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7626.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7766.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7816.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7828.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7830.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7871.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7873.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8094.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8310.xml"?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<reference anchor='DNS-bloom-filter'
 target=' https://tnc18.geant.org/getfile/3823'>
    <front>
        <title>Let a Thousand Filters Bloom. DNS-Based Threat Monitoring That Respects User Privacy</title>
        <author initials='R.' surname='van Rijswijk-Deij' fullname='Roland van Rijswijk-Deij'>
         <organization>SURFnet bv</organization>
        </author>
        <author initials='M.' surname='Bomhoff' fullname='Matthijs Bomhoff'>
         <organization>Quarantainenet B.V.</organization>
        </author>
        <author initials='R.' surname='Dolmans' fullname='Ralph Dolmans'>
         <organization>NLnet Labs Foundation</organization>
        </author>
        <date year='2018'/>
    </front>
</reference>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-capture-format.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-tcp-requirements.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-terminology-bis.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tls-dnssec-chain-extension.xml"?>
<reference anchor='Pitfalls-of-DNS-Encryption'
 target='https://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/dns-privacy/current/pdfWqAIUmEl47.pdf'>
    <front>
        <title>Pretty Bad Privacy: Pitfalls of DNS Encryption</title>
        <author initials='H.' surname='Shulman' fullname='Haya Shulman'>
            <organization>Fachbereich Informatik, Technische Universität Darmstadt</organization>
        </author>
        <date year='2014'/>
    </front>
</reference>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6841.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7525.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7686.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7706.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8198.xml"?>
<reference anchor='ipcipher-spec'
 target='https://powerdns.org/ipcipher/'>
    <front>
        <title>ipcipher: encrypting IP addresses</title>
        <author initials='B.' surname='Hubert' fullname='Bert Hubert'>
            <organization>PowerDNS</organization>
        </author>
        <date year='2018'/>
    </front>
</reference>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
